Guide to the Edward H. Durell Papers circa 1794-circa 1887 MS 1261
New-York Historical Society
Edward H. Durell papers
circa 1794-circa 1887
New-York Historical Society
Durell, Edward H. (Edward Henry), 1810-1887
MS 1261
15.8 Linear feet in 9 document boxes and 12 record cartons
The collection includes the papers of Edward H. Durell (1810-1887), originally of New Hampshire but who lived in New Orleans from 1836 to 1874. Before the Civil War, Durell primarily practiced law and was an author, publishing under the pen name Henry Didimus. After New Orleans fell to Union forces, Durell, as a Unionist, was appointed to various public positions during Reconstruction, including federal judge on the United States District Court for the District of Louisiana. The collection holds correspondence, letter books, manuscripts, extracts, diaries, notes, scrapbooks, and other documents. Represented in the collection in addition to Edward Durell are his father, Daniel Meserve Durell (1769-1841); other family and friends; his future wife, Mary Gebhard, and her circle; New Orleans merchant Aristide Miltenberger; and others.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format, with the booklets of correspondence preceding the various volumes of material.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Henry Durell (1810-1887) was born in Portsmouth, New Hampshire, a son of Daniel Meserve and Elizabeth Wentworth Durell, who had at least eight children. Daniel Meserve Durell (1769-1841), who is well-represented in the collection, was an attorney and politically active in New Hampshire, serving one term in the U.S. Congress from 1807-09, a district court judge in 1816-21, and U.S. attorney in 1830-34. Edward graduated from Harvard in 1831 and studied law with his father.
Striking out on his own, Edward Durell left New Hampshire in 1834, moving to Louisiana and settling in New Orleans in 1836. There he practiced law and began to write, including the 1845 work "New Orleans as I found it,"using the pen name H. [Henry] Didimus. For a brief time in the mid-1850s, he held local public office in New Orleans. He opposed secession, but remained in New Orleans when the Civil War broke out.
New Orleans fell to the Union forces in 1862, which led to Durell's re-engagement with public office. Among other positions, he was president of Louisiana's 1864 constitutional convention and briefly mayor of New Orleans. Durell was appointed a federal judge by President Abraham Lincoln, which led to his position on the United States District Court for the District of Louisiana in 1864.
Durell, though a Republican, seems to have had enough of an independent streak that he managed to turn both Republicans and Democrats against him, notably in response to his handling of vote counting in the 1872 presidential election. This eventually led in 1874 to Durell facing charges of corruption and drunkenness, and impeachment by the U.S. House of Representatives. Expecting conviction by the Senate, Durell resigned in 1874 and left New Orleans. Moving north, he married Mary Gebhard in New York City and then retired to Schoharie, New York for the balance of his life. He died in 1887 and was buried in Dover, New Hampshire.
(The above note was based on various on-line sources, including the 2013 M.A. thesis "Edward H. Durell, New Orleans Civic Reformer and Reconstruction Judge" by Sean C. Perry, which drew on the Durell papers.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Edward H. Durell, November 1918
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, letter books, manuscripts, extracts, diaries, notes, annotated scrapbooks of (mostly) newspaper clippings, and a catalog, all kept or collected by Edward H. Durell.
The correspondence and diaries are held in about 250 booklets. These pertain to Durell and other members of the family, including personal and romantic letters to and from Edward Durell, many in correspondence with Mary Seitz Gebhart, whom he married in 1875. Six booklets of Mary (Gebhard) Durell's correspondence of the 1880s concern her efforts to market a steam radiator for which she held a patent. Durell's father, Daniel Meserve Durell, also figures prominently in the correspondence, including some letters referring to political matters in 1806-09 when he served in Washington, DC, as a Congressman from New Hampshire. Other members of the Durell family and correspondents represented in the collection include Edward's brothers Nicholas St. John Durell, Charles J.F. Durell, and George C. Durell; sisters Elizabeth S. Durell, Sarah Adeline Durell, Mary J. Durell, and Margaret A. Durell; New Orleans merchant Aristide Miltenberger; J.S.H. Durell, John J.A. Brackett, Fanny Poor, and many others. The container list provides information as to which booklets of correspondence are in which box.
Writings in the collection include Durell's novel "The First Age"; extracts from military general orders, most originating from the headquarters of the Dept. of the Gulf in New Orleans (1 volume, 1862-1865); extracts from the New Orleans newspaper "Daily True Delta" (2 volumes, 1860-1864); extracts from the Shreveport newspaper "South-Western" (2 volumes, 1861-1866); manuscript of stories (2 volumes); an annotated version of "New Orleans as I Found It" by H. Didimus (Durell's pen name); and a translation of P.C. Roux's essay on the history of France, including Durell's notes.
Finally, the collection holds 49 other volumes. Of these, 34 consist almost exclusively of annotated newspaper clippings and 2 appear to be an index to some or all of the clippings. Durell inscribed all of these clippings scrapbooks with a quotation from the English writer Thomas de Quincey to describe their content: "Crude undigested masses of suggestion, furnishing rather raw material for composition and jotting for the memory, than any formal development of ideas." But they generally seem to pertain to national political matters, especially with regard to the South. Volumes 1-27 of the clippings are indexed at least in part (many of the 1880s clippings in the volumes seem to have been added after the indexing was done); volumes 29-34 are not indexed. Other than clippings there are 11 volumes of documents related to Louisiana history and two of miscellaneous essays from various publications.
Louisiana -- Politics and government.; Louisiana -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; New Orleans (La.) -- Description and travel.; New Orleans (La.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; Judges -- Louisiana.; Diaries.; Excerpts.; Letter books.; Letters (correspondence); Manuscripts (documents); Newspaper clippings.; Scrapbooks.; Durell, Daniel Meserve, 1769-1841; Dorrell family; United States. Army. Department of the Gulf (1862-1865); United States. District Court (Louisiana)
- Durell family records, 1794-1865 (Offsite-box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  * 17 booklets labeled "Diary of DMD" [Daniel Meserve Durell], 1794-1841.
  * 14 booklets labeled "Family records, EHD" [Edward H. Durell].
  * A few labeled "family records" (roughly 1700s-1865).
- Durell family records, 1820s-1880s (Offsite-box 2)
  * 9 booklets of diaries of Durell's wife, Mary S. Durell, starting with her wedding day, June 8, 1875, ending later in 1875, with some undated booklets.
  * 11 booklets labeled "Family letters to EHD" (1870s-80s).
  * 14 booklets labeled "Letters to EHD" (1870s-80s).
  * 3 booklets labeled "Letters of EHD" (1820s-30s).
- Durell family records, 1830s-1880s (Offsite-box 3)
  24 booklets labeled "Letters of EHD." The label of one of the booklets also refers to letters of Charles J.F. Durell.
- Durell family records, 1870s-1880s (Offsite-box 4)
  * 30 booklets labeled "Letters of EHD" (1870s-80s).
  * 6 booklets labeled "Letters of EHD to AM" [Aristide Miltenberger] (1870s).
- Durell family records, 1840s-1880s (Offsite-box 5)
  * 6 booklets labeled "Letters of EHD to AM" [Aristide Miltenberger] (1870s-80s).
  * 17 booklets labeled "Letters to MSD" [Mary S. Durell] (1870s-80s).
  * 1 booklet "Letters of Miss Fannie Robinson to MSD" (1860s).
  * 7 booklets "Letters Miscellaneous to MSD" (1860s-70s).
  * 2 booklets "Letters of John J.A. Brackett to MSD" (1860s).
  * 8 booklets "Letters of MSD" (1840s-70s).
- Durell family records, 1802-1870s (Offsite-box 6)
  * 1 booklet labeled "Letters of John J.A. Brackett & Fanny Poor to MSD [Mary S. Durell]" (1860s).
  * 4 booklets labeled "Letters of Fannie Poor to MSD" (1860-70s).
  * 1 booklet labeled "Letters of Fannie Poor & the Misses Betts to MSD" [various names] (1860s).
  * 4 booklets labeled "Letters of the Misses Betts to MSD" (1860s-70s).
  * 8 booklets labeled "Letters of DMD" [Daniel Meserve Durell](1802-1830s).
  * 4 booklets labeled "Letters from & to Nicholas St. John Durell, 1822-26"
- Durell family records, 1817-1880s (Offsite-box 7)
  * 4 booklets labeled "Letters from & to Nicholas St. John Durell, 1822 to 1826".
  * 2 booklets labeled "Letters of GCD [George C. Durell] (1830s).
  * 1 booklet labeled "Letters of MJD [Mary Jane Durell] & SAD [S.A. Durell/S. Adeline Green] (1817-1850s).
  * 2 booklets "Letters of SAD" (1830s-50s).
  * 6 booklets labeled "Letters of CJFD" [Charles J.F. Durell] (1820s-30s).
  * 6 booklets labeled "Letters"; these are letters to EHD (1860s-80s).
- Durell family records, 1830s-80s (Offsite-box 8)
  * 2 booklets of "Index."
  * 8 booklets with letters of GCD [George C. Durell], MJD [Mary Jane Durell], (mostly) ESD [Elizabeth S. Durell], MAD [Margaret A. Durell], and JSHD [John Samuel H. Durell] (1820s-60s).
  * 8 booklets labeled "Miscellaneous letters"; these range from 1806-1860s and include letters to various members of the Durell family. These include many letters to Daniel Meserve Durell from 1806-09 when he was a Representative in Washington, DC, and these seem to refer to political matters of the time.
  * 3 booklets of EHD investment transaction correspondence and accounts with the firm of John J. Cisco & Son (1870s-80s).
  * 6 booklets concerning Mary S. Durell's efforts to market a steam radiator for which she held patent number 347,476 (1880s).
  * 5 booklets of calling cards.
- Various, circa 1880s (Offsite-box 9)
  * 4 booklets of calling cards.
  * 2 booklets of "notes" or copies of letters (1880s).
  * Notes from clippings.
  * Excerpts from books and indexes to book sources.
  * Record of letters received and sent from March 1876-April 1887.
- Bound volumes, 1840s?-1860s? (Offsite-box 10)
  * 2 volumes of extracts from the "Southwestern," Shreveport, Louisiana newspaper, 1860-66.
  * 2 volumes of extracts from the "Daily True Delta," New Orleans, Louisiana newspaper, 1860-61, 1863-64.
  * 1 volume of extracts of "selections from military general orders, 1862-65" and other miscellaneous documents.
  * 2 volumes of manuscript "Stories" (likely written by Durell).
  * 2 volumes of manuscript of "The First Age".
  * 2 volumes transcript and notes of "History of France" by P. C. Roux, as translated by H. Didimus.
- Bound volumes, 1840s?-1870s (Offsite-box 11)
  * 2 volumes (embossed as "Stories"), with transcripts of EHD's letters to Mary Gebhard and, then, Mary Durell, his wife, 1872-1878.
  * 5 volumes of transcripts of letters, 1847-65.
  * 2 volumes of transcripts of letters, 1847-73.
  * One volume of notes from EHD's reading diary.
  * 1 volume "catalogue of books read," 1870s?
  * Book "New Orleans as I found it" by H. Didimus, inscribed to Durell by the author, and correspondence and notes tipped in.
- "Louisiana Debate" (Box 1 of 2). Volumes 1-5, 1852-1877 (Offsite-box 12)
  Scrapbooks holding clippings of published works, with Durell's annotations, notes; copies of the published journals of debates of the Louisiana House, Senate, and constitutional convention; and various government reports "touching the administration of Louisiana."
- "Louisiana Debate" (Box 2 of 2). Volumes 6-8, 1862-1878 (Offsite-box 13)
- "Louisiana Legislation" (Box 1 of 2). Volumes 1, 2, 1860-1870 (Offsite-box 13)
  These scrapbooks hold copies of legislative bills, acts, resolutions, and the like.
- "Louisiana Legislation" (Box 2 of 2). Volume 3, 1868-1877 (Offsite-box 14)
- "Clippings" (Box 1 of 8). Volumes 1, 2 (RESTRICTED), 1860-1876 (Offsite-box 15)
  Conditions Governing Access
  These two volumes were shrinkwrapped in 1994 because of the presence of mold. Access to these volumes is permitted only after consultation with, and permission from, the manuscripts curator and the conservator.
- "Clippings" (Box 2 of 8). Volumes 3-7, 1855-1885 (Offsite-box 14)
- "Clippings" (Box 3 of 8). Volumes 8-13, 1870-1880s (Offsite-box 16)
- "Clippings" (Box 4 of 8). Volumes 14-18, 1878-1880s (Offsite-box 17)
- "Clippings" (Box 5 of 8). Volumes 19-23, 1878-1880s (Offsite-box 18)
- "Clippings" (Box 6 of 8). Volumes 24-28, 1858-1880s (Offsite-box 19)
  Volume 26 consists mostly of two published works: "Recollections of Henry Watson Allen" by Sarah A. Dorsey, and "Louisiana As It Is" by Daniel Dennett.
- "Clippings" (Box 7 of 8). Volumes 29-33, 1856-1881 (Offsite-box 20)
- "Clippings" (Box 8 of 8). Volumes 34, 1865-1881 (Offsite-box 21)
- "Selections" Volumes 1, 2, 1868-1882 (Offsite-box 21)
  Volume 1 holds mostly articles from North American Review; Volume 2 holds mostly articles from International Review, Princeton Review, and Atlantic Monthly.
- "Indexes" Volumes 1,2, undated (Offsite-box 21)
  Appears to relate to the clippings volumes.